Hi, and welcome to this course on MCP server security.
Before we dive into vulnerabilities and attacks,
we need to understand what MCP is and why it exists.
MCP stands for Model Context Protocol.
It's a standard way to make external application
provide context to LLM models.
So what does that actually mean?
Imagine you use an AI model like Claude or Chab GBT.
With this model, you can enable online search
where the model can search the web for you
or you can enable a tool that will allow the model
to create an image for you.
So those are like built-in capabilities.
However, if you ask the model to sort your files on Google Drive
or maybe summarize your email from Gmail
or translate your private YouTube videos
into a language like German
or maybe access a content from your Contentful CMS solution,
then in this case, the LLM model
won't be able to do that out of the box.
So why the LLM model cannot access your data?
There are two main reasons for that.
First, the LLM is not designed to access external systems
directly.
They are designed to generate text based on the user input
that they receive.
The second reason is the LLM are not aware
of the context of your external systems.
So they do not really know how to authenticate
for example to your Google Drive
or how to use Contentful Management Authorization
token to access your website content that is hosted on Contentful.
Oh, MCP comes to solve this problem.
MCP is the universal connector.
So MCP gives you a standard way to build a server
that can connect the LLM model to an external applications
and APIs just like USB-C.
It lets you connect any device to your computer.
So MCP lets you connect any data source
like Google Drive or maybe YouTube
or maybe Contentful to your AI model.
Once it's connected, you can ask the LLM
to interact with your data
and you can simply say list my files on Google Drive
and then maybe sort them by size.
Let's walk through a real example.
When a user asks list or get all my files on Google Drive
and then maybe sort them by size.
Here's what's going to happen behind the scenes.
The LLM is going to check if there is an MCP server integration
that can handle this specific request.
It finds out that Google Drive MCP server
and then it sends the request to the MCP server.
The MCP server is going to authenticate
against Google using your authorization token.
After that, the MCP is able to fetch file names
and metadata through Google API.
Once it gets that, it will return this data back
to the LLM model.
Now at this stage, the LLM can now generate a response
with your actual files sorted by size back to the user.
The magic is that the LLM model itself
it never touches the Google Drive.
The MCP is the one that handles all the complex authentication
and API calls.
Get the data from Google Drive, send it back to the LLM model
and once the LLM model has the data like files metadata,
it can sort them and send them back to the user
based on the user request.
Now let's take a business use case
to help you understand how powerful the MCP server is.
Imagine you work for a company that has a website
and they host their website content on a CMS solution
like Contentful.
And you have a task to translate the website content
into a new language, let's say, German.
Typically what you have to do, first,
you need to get the latest blog post using Contentful API
or maybe manually through their user interface.
Once you get the content, then you need to go to the AI model
for the translation.
If you are satisfied with the translation,
you need to go back to Contentful and then publish or update
the translated content back to Contentful.
And this is a lot of manual work.
However, with MCP, you can automate the entire workflow
and do all of this work inside the LLM conversation itself.
So basically you can do the entire workflow
inside Cloud Disktop.
With MCP, you can ask the LLM to translate the latest blog post
into German.
Again, LLM will check for a Contentful MCP server integration.
If there is one, it will send the request to that MCP server.
The Contentful MCP server, first, it will authenticate
to Contentful using your token.
Second, it will fetch your blog post content
and then it will return it back to the LLM.
At this point, the LLM will translate the text
and here is the powerful part.
It can ask you if you are satisfied with that translation.
And if this is the case, if you are satisfied with the translation,
then again, the LLM can publish the translated content back
into Contentful using the same MCP server.
Now, at this point, you have a German version
of your website content automatically created and published.
I brought this example to highlight that the MCP server
can provide both read and write access to your data,
which is very, very powerful.
This was a very high level overview of how MCP works.
In my opinion, MCP is a game changer
because it transforms the LLM from isolated text generator
into powerful assistance that can access and modify your data.
And that opens the door to a new vulnerabilities
and a new attack vectors.
In the next lectures, we will dive deeper
into MCP architecture and implementation
and we will start building a local MCP server.
I hope this picture has been informative for you
and I would love to see you in the next lecture.
Thanks for watching.